Guide to the Albert F. Murray papers, 1858-1987 MS2003
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Albert F. Murray papers
1858-1987
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Murray, Albert F.
MS2003
6 Linear Feet
Collection relates primarily to Albert F. Murray's career and includes information about his early years working on radio-controlled torpedoes and later his work with the development of television. The material related to television is one of the stronger portions of the collection and includes many photographs, patents, schematics, a chronological history of RCA-Victor, and numerous journal and newspaper articles.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The Albert F. Murray Papers was donated in 1984 by his widow Elizabeth Murray.
Biographical Note
Albert F. Murray (1894-1984) a pioneer in hi-fidelity television development, had a long and successful engineering career in both the U.S. military and private industry. Murray was born in Decatur, Alabama in 1894 and died in Bethesda, Maryland in 1984. Murray received bachelor degrees from Maryville College in Tennessee and from MIT and Harvard. Following his graduation from Harvard in 1918, Murray joined the Engineering Reserve Corps and served as a 1st Lieutenant in the United States Army Air Service in 1918. He left formal military service in 1918, but his early engineering work was on a project for the Navy and during WWII he worked with the National Defense Research Committee and the Office of Scientific Research and Development. Murray's engineering career began with his work in 1919 for the Hammond Radio Research Laboratory. This work culminated in 1924 with the design and operation of the first successful underwater radio controlled torpedo built for the United States Navy. Following his work for Hammond, Murray held many engineering jobs including those with the Wireless Specialty Apparatus Co., Raytheon, Jenkins Television Corporation, RCA-Victor, Co., and the Philco Television Co. As head of the Television Department at Philco, Murray conducted the first public demonstration of high-fidelity television at the Franklin Institute in Philadelphia in 1937. Following his work for the government during WWII, Murray worked as an independent consulting television engineer based in Washington, D.C. Murray was a member of many engineering and honorary societies, he wrote extensively, and presented lectures about television. Many of these lectures accompanied television demonstrations. Murray's work with early television is the most well known part of a long and successful engineering career.
Collection Scope and Content
The dates of the bulk of the material in the collection are 1920-43. The material within the collection relates primarily to Albert F. Murray's career and includes information about his early years working on radio-controlled torpedoes and later his work with the development of television. The material related to television is one of the stronger portions of the collection and includes many photographs, patents, schematics, a chronological history of RCA-Victor, and numerous journal and newspaper articles. During WWII, Murray left his job at Philco Television to join the government. He worked primarily with the National Defense Research Committee. In this capacity he visited inventors and laboratories to study inventions and report on their potential usefulness for the military. Among the inventions investigated by Murray included radio masking tools, interference generators, and Death Ray machines. Please note that there is a folder in the Series Patents and Inventions also related to Death Ray machines.
Murray's work with the John Hays Hammond Laboratory is detailed in a series related to his work with remote controlled torpedoes. The series includes progress reports and other similar reporting tools used by Murray to describe the successes and failures of the program from 1919 to 1924. These reports include quite a bit of science as Murray describes the data gathered during testing and also the engineering methods used to overcome difficulties with design and performance.
Collection Organization
Organized into 16 series: Artifacts, Biographical information, Correspondence, Diary, Employment, Graphics, Maps, Miscellaneous, Patents and inventions, Presentations, Publications and writings, Phonograph records, Scrapbooks, Television, Torpedo, and Oversize.
Photographs; Maps; Radio; Torpedoes; Washington (D.C.); Scrapbooks; Diaries; Inventions; Electrical engineers; Television; Hammond Radio Research Laboratory; United States. Office of Research and Development; RCA-A Victor Company, inc.; Raytheon Company; Philco Corporation; Murray, Albert F.
- Artifacts, 1924-1936; MS2003 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This is a small series of material related to Murray's career.
  - Artifacts, 1924-1936 (Box 1)
  - Atlantic Telegraph Cable Guaranteed by Tiffany & Co. Broadway, NY, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Gold card-lifetime member of the Institute of Radio Engineers, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Key that controlled the first submerged radio controlled torpedo, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - NBC tenth anniversary medal, 1926-1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Biographical information, undated; MS2003 Series 2; 0.1 Linear feet
  The material within the biography series relates to Murray's engineering career and includes biographies for inclusion in Who's Who in Engineering and a detailed introduction written when Murray received an honorary degree from Maryville College.
  - Biographical information, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1858-1978; MS2003 Series 3; 0.1 Linear feet
  The letters in this series mostly relate to Murray's career and include his letter of resignation from the Philco Corporation in 1939 and his work with the National Defense Research Committee that began in 1940. There are a couple of letters between Murray and Dr. W. R. G. Baker of General Electric discussing the advantages and disadvantages of color television. Series V: Employment has letters of recommendation. Therefore, the letters in this series and the letters in that series compliment each other to form a more complete picture of Murray's professional life.
  - Correspondence, 1858-1978 [1929-1978] (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Diary, 1941-1945; MS2003 Series 4; 0.5 Linear feet
  The three diaries in this series all relate to the work Murray did during WWII, specifically with the Office of Scientific Research and Development and National Defense Research Committee. These diaries are typed notes of meetings he attended and laboratories he visited. This material chronicles his visits to laboratories and other work for this organization including Murray's work investigating Death Ray machines. Two additional folders identical in layout and content, but without the designation diary were added to this series. These folders are part of Murray's work with the National Defense Research Committee. Using these four folders together allows people to have a good look at the work Murray did from 1941-43.
  - Office of Scientific Research and Development, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - National Defense Research Committee, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - National Defense Research Committee, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - National Defense Research Committee, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Employment, undated; MS2003 Series 5; 0.25 Linear feet
  The material in this series is related primarily to his employment with the government. The letters of recommendation are mainly for government jobs in the late 1910s and early 1920s.
  - General, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters of recommendation, 1915-1923 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Graphics, 1915-1960; MS2003 Series 6; 1.5 Linear feet
  The graphics are entirely composed of photographic prints. Many of the photographs were originally part of photo albums. All the photographs were removed from harmful mounts, stored in protective sleeves, and place in acid-free folders in the original order. There are a limited number of images that remain with the reports they are associated with. The topics include Murray's work with the torpedoes, television including staff images from RCA and transmitted images from Philco. There are a small number of personal images
  - Album A [1/2], undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Album A [2/2], undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Album B [1/2], undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Album B [2/2], undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Album C [1/2], undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Album C [2/2], undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Album D [1/2], undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Album D [2/2], undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Committee on Science and the Arts of the Franklin Institute Philadephia PA, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Cruft high tension electrical laboratory, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - German post office, 1936 November 06 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - I.R.E. Philadephia section, 1934 May 27 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Maryville College, Circa 1915 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Miltary Cuba WWI (radio), undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Military Navy Sonar, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Graphics, 1920-1953 (Box 4)
  - Military (general), undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - N.T.S.C., 1953 April 09 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Philco, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Philco, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Philco, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Philco, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Philco, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Raytheon engineering department, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - RCA Victor, Co. inc research division, 1932 May (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - RCA Victor Radio-tv, 1930-1939 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Torpedo Gloucester site of early John Hays Hammond Laboratory, 1930-1939 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Torpedo John Hays Hammond Laboratory, 1920-1929 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Torpedo u.s. radio controlled torpedo under Hammond sponsorship, 1920-1929 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Graphics, undated (Box 5)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified [several are called Direction Finder possibly in Newport, RI], undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Maps, undated; MS2003 Series 7; 0.1 Linear feet
  This small series includes one folder with several maps from WWII.
  - WWII war map, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous, undated; MS2003 Series 8; 0.3 Linear feet
  This is a catchall series for materials that did not fit into the other series. The folders are arranged in alphabetical order. The folder topics include a conference at American University in 1948, a folder for Edwin H. Armstrong, and materials about the adoption of the metric system.
  - Edwin H. Armstrong, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Conference American University American Public Relations Association First International Public Relations Institute "Public Relations... for a free world", 3rd annual convention, 1948 May (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Decible charts General Radio Company, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Electron devices meeting, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Franklin Institute, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Engineering exhibits of Hughes Tool Company, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Adoption of metric system, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - NASA Satellite, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Notebook from MIT, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Railroad [writings by Murray], undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Patents and inventions, 1925-1959; MS2003 Series 9; 0.1 Linear feet
  This series includes applications and other written explanations of patents and inventions. Only some of the inventions are by Murray. One of the more interesting folders is the one about the inventions of Death Ray machines. Murray has a handwritten description of his experience with Death Ray machines during WWII. He explains that his study of Death Ray machine is limited the investigations done by the National Defense Research Committee. The folder includes descriptions of visits Murray made to test the Death Ray machines invented by various people.
  - Death ray, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - General inventions written by Murray, 1925-1939 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    General note
    descriptions and patent applications
  - General patent applications, 1925 May 25 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    handwritten drawings and outlines for inventions in preparing instruction
  - Military Electronic Procurement Directory, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Radiant engery system application with schematics, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Radio, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    amateur radio station application for license for Murray and information for the MIT Wireless Society
  - Transmitting system for radiant energy, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Presentations, 1929-1963; MS2003 Series 10; 0.2 Linear feet
  This series includes speeches, lectures, and statements most often by Murray. The primary topic is television.
  - Address by Dr. Chalmers W. Sherwin "The Management of Science and Technology in the Public Interest: A Challenge to the Scientific Community", 1963 September 09 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Radiovision, 1929 November (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Broadcasting of Radiovision talk given before the college of the City of New York Radio Club by A.F. Murray.
  - "Teledynamics" broadcast appearance by Murray, 1935 July 06 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Lecture about television and facsimile A.I.E.E., 1938 October 31 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Television frequency allocations report of the Television Committee of the Radio Manufactures Association of the FCC [presentation by Murray], undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Murray speech for Segei A. Schelkunoff, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Schelkunoff is receiving an award.
  - Television progress speech by Murray, 1937 January 12 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Television, speech, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Statement Utilization of Frequencies in the Band 470 to 890 Mcs for television broadcasting on behalf of the Philco Corporation, 1950 October (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Publications and writings, 1917-1987; MS2003 Series 11; 1 Linear feet
  This is a large series that includes articles, journals, magazines, one book, newspaper articles papers, and reports. The folder title indicates if Murray is the author. Series XIII: Scrapbooks also has newspaper articles and should not be overlooked if looking for this type of information.
  - "An automotive battery charging panel", undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - "Can we multiplex our radio channels?" Radio Broadcast, 1928 September (Box 6, Folder 16)
    Subseries 1: Articles written by Albert F. Murray
  - "The desirability of cooperation between the television and motion picture industries", 1938 December 15 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - "Highlights of FCC color hearings and demostrations to date, including a tabulation of characteristics comparing the various competative systems" Tele Tech, 1949 November (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - "How was reception last night?", undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - "Measurement of fidelity in television systems" Electronics, 1931 October (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - "The RMA television synchronizing signal proposed for use in the U.S.A.", undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - "Project 'Tinkertoy' step toward the automotive factory" Tele Tech, 1953 November (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - "Receiving antennas" Chapters V and VIII in the Boston Post Book of Radio Knowledge, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - "Shielding HF interference" Electronic Industries, 1945 August (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - "What's Ahead for Television" Rochester Engineer [pgs. 78-82], 1938 November (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Untitled article from publication Communications, 1938 December (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - "E.M.I. Cathode-Ray Television Transmission Tubes" by J.D. McGee and H. G. Lubszynski, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    Subseries 2: Articles not written by Albert F. Murray
  - "Laser Weapon Update" by Alison Bass Diagram: Piezo Electric Products, Inc., 1983 November - December (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - "Making Room for the Medium" New York Times Magazine, 1981 September 27 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - "Paying the Engineer" no author Electronic Industries, 1945 November (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - "Transmission of Electromagnetic Waves in Hollow Tubes of Metal" W.L. Barrow, 1936 October (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - The History of Television 1880-1941 by Albert Abramson, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    Subseries 3: Book
  - "Journal of the Franklin Institute", 1948 February (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Subseries 4: Journals
  - "Journal of the Franklin Institute", 1949 December (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "R.M.A. Engineer" (article by Murray), 1938 November (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "The Boston Post Book of Radio Knowledge Vol. II" [article by Murray], undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Douglas Airview" [no. 11], 1945 November - December (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Subseries 5: Magazines
  - "Electronics World", 1968 January (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Flying Bombs", 1944 December (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "Harper's" [article commented on by Murray], 1981 January (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "Impact Air Victory Over Japan", 1945 September - October (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - "Skyline" North American Aviation, Inc., Vol. 16 No. 2, 1958 September (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "Television News," March-April 1932 [article by Murray] (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "Television and Short-wave World", 1938 May (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - "The Wireless Age", 1917 February (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - "Commerce Business Daily U.S.," Department of Commerce, 1962 March 13 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    Subseries 6: Newsletter
  - Newspaper articles, 1923-1983 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    Subseries 7: Newspaper articles
  - Automotive Testing and Charging Equipment Lanagan & Hoke Philadelphia, PA, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
    Subseries 8: Pamphlets
  - How to Sell to the United States Armed Forces in Europe, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - The Tape Recorder as an Instrumentation Device by Paul J. Weber, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - The TV Antenna Story American Phenolic Corp., undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - UHF Television RCA, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - The Design Techniques and Performance Limits of Multistage Thermoelectric Devices by Irving I. Sochard, 1961 [abstract] (Box 7, Folder 21)
    Subseries 9: Papers
  - A Germanium Ultra High Speed Switching Transistor by Doyle Granberry, 1961 [abstract] (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Injecting Carrier Concentrations in Diffused Silicon Transistors by observations of Interband Carrier Recombination by N.J. Chaplin, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Injecting Carrier Concentrations in Diffused Silicon KMC Silicon Planar Transistors, 1961 [abstract] (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - A Multi-position Magnetic Core Drive Using Electron Beam Switched P-N Junctions, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Semi-conductor Delay Line Tuner by John S. Winslow, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Television Goes Touring by Albert F. Murray, undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Guided Missiles in U.S.A., 1945 March (Box 7, Folder 28)
    Subseries 10: Reports and unpublished materials
  - Life Test of Airesearch Time Dwell Servo Valve 56000-2 Model TSV102-1-1 Richard Colgan, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Television topics chapters written by various authors, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Vacuum tubes inductance coils, tuning charts, transmitting circuits [possibly chapters in book by Abramson], undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Electronics Installation and Servicing Handbook, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Subseries 11: Service manuals
  - Monarch Record Changer operation instructions, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - RCA Radiola 51(DC), undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Philco Television and Phonograph, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Westinghouse Radio, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Phonograph records, undated; MS2003 Series 12; 1 Linear feet
  The records are classical music.
  - "African Lament", undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "Chason Indove" (song of India), undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "Deep in My Heart Students' March." by Jesse Crawford, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "A Dream," Enrico Caruso, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "Duna Reinald Werrenrath", undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - "Gems from 'Pirates of Penzance'," Gilbert and Sullivan Part 1, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - "Gems from 'Pirates of Penzance'" Gilbert and Sullivan Part 4, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - "Holy Ghost, with Light Devine Choir of the Riverside Church", undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - "The Hunt Dexter Gordon and Wardell Gray," Part 8, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - "I'm in Love Again Henri Rene and his orchestra" [broken], undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - "La Boheme Puccini", undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - "Lonesome and Sorry-Fox Trot", undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - "Lover Come Back to Me" Lawrence Tibbett, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - "Maiden with Flaxen Hair Debussy", undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - "Millicent-Waltz Hesitation Victor Military Band", undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - "Ol'Man River" John Charles Thomas, undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - "La Paloma (The Dove)" Victor Salon Orchestra, undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - "Piece En Forme De Habanera" Mischa Elman, undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - "Puritani O te o cara amor talora (To Thee Oh Dearest)" Miguel Fleta [Act I], undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - "Show Boat" medley by Jesse Crawford, undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - "Serenata" Alma Gluck, undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - "Spinning Song" Ignace Jan Paderewski [Part 2], undated (Box 9, Folder 22)
- Scrapbooks, 1925-1937; MS2003 Series 13; 0.25 Linear feet
  The scrapbooks were primarily composed of newspaper articles. For preservation purposes the newspaper articles were photocopied and kept in their original order. In addition to the newspaper articles, the scrapbooks have pamphlets, photographs, and program flyers.
  - Scrapbook [mostly newspaper clippings], 1925-1929 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1930-1937 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, newspaper articles, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, personal, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, No. 1 [pamphlets in back], undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Television, 1921-1964; MS2003 Series 14; 2 Linear feet
  The material in this subject-oriented series relates primarily to work done by Murray. Much of the collection material as a whole relates to television and thus any researcher pursing that topic will need to review material in other series, but these folders have material specifically and exclusively relating to television and therefore warranted inclusion in a subject-oriented series. The topics include standards, the Federal Communications Commission, service manuals, the history of RCA, and Philco schematics.
  - Farnsworth Television System, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - FCC the Communications Act of 1934 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - FCC Rules and Regulations Telecommunications, 1939-1940 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - FCC Standards of Good Engineering Television Broadcast Stations (Channels 1-18), 1941 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Ground wave Signal Range Television, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - History Development of Television in Research Division of RCA, Victor, Inc., 1930-1932 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - History Development of Television in Research Division of RCA, Victor, Inc., 1932 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Inventions Television related products, 1921 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Inventions Television, 1928-1939 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Manual Philco Radio and Television service bulletins, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Manual Sylvania Color Television, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Meeting Television Systems Committee #22, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Notebook Department 5841 Television and Ultra-high frequency Receivers, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Press release, 1937 February 11 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Schematics Philco Co., undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Standards: of good engineering practice 550-1600 KC, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Standards: Rules FM and TV Stations and Standards and High Frequency Broadcasts, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)